Hi again. In the last video,
we focused on how to close out
a project for your
customer and stakeholders.
In this video, we'll discuss
the best practices for closing
a project with your team.
You'll also learn to
use a retrospective to
close your project and
celebrate your team's
accomplishments.
I've talked to you
about retrospectives
quite a bit throughout
this program, and
that's because there really is
no better tool for
reflection and improvement.
Retrospectives are such
an important aspect of
the project, and it's important to
really emphasize that to you.
Throughout the course, I'm
referring to the formal practice,
but a lot of us conduct
informal retrospectives daily
without even knowing it.
Whether we're talking about
our day with our
friends or family
or thinking about how we can
improve past interactions,
we are constantly reflecting
and working toward progress.
Let's revisit formal
retrospectives
for a moment to explore
how they tie into the formal
project closing process.
You might remember
that a retrospective
is a meeting aimed to
discuss successes,
failures, and possible
improvements on the project.
They can occur after
a major milestone completion
and at the end of a project.
In order to understand
the importance of
closing a project,
let's discuss the three main
retrospective benefits
for your team.
Retrospectives encourage
team-building because they
allow team members to understand
differing perspectives.
Retrospectives facilitate
improved collaboration
on future projects,
and they promote positive changes
in future procedures
and processes.
So it's no surprise that
a retrospective is a critical
part of closing a project.
Whether your team has
chosen to close the project
after each phase or
comprehensively at the end,
you'll conduct retrospectives
as a part of that process.
There may be temptation
within your project
team to resist
reflecting before forging
ahead into the next phase,
but you can't grow and improve if
you don't spend time reflecting.
Reflecting is a great way to
learn which practices you
should keep doing and which
ones you can improve upon.
As a project manager,
you want to build a culture
within your team and
company to aim for
constant improvements.
This means that you'll
need to solicit
feedback that will help you to
do better in your next project.
This feedback might touch on
any aspect of the project,
from planning,
scheduling, execution,
communication, or team dynamics.
You might receive feedback about
processes you led,
and that's okay.
Working through
feedback is crucial to
your growth as a project manager.
It's important to create
a safe space for that
feedback so that
folks can really
share what they're
thinking and the team
can grow together.
This is a key piece
to help improve
collaborations on
future projects.
Part of encouraging
continuous growth is
to recognize and celebrate
a job well done.
The way you celebrate will
change depending on
where you're at in
the project and what feels
most appropriate to your team.
Taking a moment to reward
yourself with a token of
appreciation turns
the celebration
into a team-building exercise.
Being appreciative ensures
that the work you're
doing feels uplifting
and rewarding,
rather than monotonous
and tiring.
It also fuels positive change.
So when closing a project,
don't forget the fun elements.
Makes sure to play a
game, eat some cake,
and celebrate some quality time
together, because
you've earned it.
Let's review. Retrospectives
encourage team-building
because they allow team members
to understand differing
perspectives.
They facilitate
improved collaboration
on future projects,
and they promote
positive changes in
future procedures and processes.
Now that you know how to wrap
things up for your team,
let's discuss how to wrap
everything up for
the project manager.